Guide to the Clifton Fadiman Papers
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Clifton Fadiman Papers
1966-1970.
Fadiman, Clifton, 1904-1999.
1.5 linear feet (3 document boxes).
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library, New York, NY.
4078748
This collection includes drafts of the writings of author and editor Clifton Fadiman.
Biographical Note
Clifton P. Fadiman (1904-1999), known to friends as Kip, was a well-known author, editor, and broadcast personality. Born in Brooklyn to Russian immigrant parents, Fadiman developed an interest in language and literature very early on. He attended Columbia University, and graduated Phi Beta Kappa in 1925. After beginning his career as an editor at Simon and Schuster, Fadiman worked as the book review editor for The New Yorker from 1933 to 1943. In 1938, Fadiman was hired as the host of a radio quiz show called Information Please. The show ran for over ten years; after it was taken off the air, Fadiman hosted a number of other radio and television programs.
In 1944 Fadiman became an editor and judge for the Book-of-the-Month club, a position he held for over fifty years. He was also a consultant and contributor to the Encyclopaedia Britannica, for which he wrote an article on children's literature of which he was especially proud. Children's literature was a life-long interest; he edited the World Treasury of Children's Literature, published in 1984, and wrote a book review column in the children's magazine Cricket (of which he was a senior editor). Fadiman was an extremely prolific author, writing on subjects from poetry to mathematics to wine, and the editor of numerous anthologies and collections. In 1993 he was honored with the National Book Foundation Medal for Distinguished Contribution to American Letters.
Fadiman married Pauline Elizabeth Rush in 1927. The couple had a son, Jonathan Rush. In 1949 they divorced, and Fadiman married Annalee Jacoby the next year. They had two children, Kim and Anne. Fadiman died of pancreatic cancer at the age of 95.
Scope and Content
The collection consists mainly of drafts, both hand-written and typed, for various writings and lectures. Particularly well-represented is Fadiman's work for Encyclopaedia Britannica and the Book-of-the-Month club. Some correspondence and research materials are also included in the collection.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in 4 series, the contents of each arranged alphabetically.
Series I. Writings, 1966-1969
Series II. Lectures, 1967-1969
Series III. Encyclopedia Britannica, 1967-1970
Subseries III.1. Article on Children's Literature, undated
Subseries III.2. Other Projects, 1967-1970
Series IV. Book-of-the-Month Club, undated
Subjects
Fadiman, Clifton, 1904-1999.; Moore, Clement Clarke, 1779-1863.; Scherman, Harry, b. 1887.; Van Doren, Mark, 1894-1972.; Book-of-the-Month Club.; Encyclopaedia Britannica, inc.; Children's literature.; Encyclopedias and dictionaries.; Literature.; lecture notes; manuscripts (document genre); obituaries; reviews (document genre); typescripts; Authors.; Editors.; Encyclopaedia Britannica.
Acquisition
1969 M-69 Fadiman, Clifton
Related Material-- at Columbia
George Macy Papers, 1916-1970 at the Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Gilbert Highet Papers, 1929-1978 at the Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Ralph Thompson Papers 1944-1956 at the Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Reminiscences of Clifton Fadiman: oral history, 1955 at the Oral History Research Office, Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Series I: Writings, 1966-1969
  This series consists of various writing projects, including the obituary of Harry Scherman, a fellow Columbia graduate and the founder of the Book-of-the-Month club, and the forewords to several books. In the case of A Visit from Saint Nicholas, correspondence and research materials on Clement Clark Moore sent to Fadiman by his publisher are included in addition to Fadiman's drafts of the introduction. The series also contains an essay entitled "What Makes a Teacher Great?" about Mark van Doren, who taught at Columbia from 1920 to 1959.
  - Anthology of Monsters Foreword, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Annual, Famous Writers Foreword ,1969 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - "Art, Wine, and Wine Merchants," circa 1969 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    (Essay in Sherry-Lehmann Summer Sale Catalog)
  - Obituary of Harry Scherman, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Study on Instructional Technology--Academy for Education and Development, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - A Visit from Saint Nicholas,1966 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    (Introduction, Correspondence, and Research Materials)
  - "What Makes a Teacher Great?", 1968 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Series II: Lectures, 1967-1969
  This series is comprised of Fadiman's notes for several lectures on the topics of literature and communication.
  - American Council on the Teaching of Foreign Languages (New Orleans), 1969 November 2 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - "Communication in the Arts: A Practitioner's Notes," 1968 May 2 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - "The Enjoyment of Literature: A Study in Obsolescence--Part I: Looking Backward"--UCLA, 1967 February 6 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - "The Enjoyment of Literature: A Study in Obsolescence--Part II: Looking Around"--UCLA, 1967 February 8 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - "A Light Verse Carnival"--International Poetry Forum, 1969 April 9 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - "Literature in the Ice Age"--University of Chicago, 1967 November 1 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Series III: Encyclopedia Britannica, 1967-1970
  This series contains drafts of and papers relating to Fadiman's work for the Encyclopaedia Britannica Company.
  - Subseries I: Article on Children's Literature, undated
    Included in this sub-series are research materials and numerous drafts of the article on children's literature that Fadiman wrote for the Britannica.
    - Background--General, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Background--Countriesl, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Drafts, undated, (4 folders) (Box 2, Folder 3 to 6)
    - Final Typescript, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Subseries II: Other projects, 1967-1970
    This sub-series contains documents related to some of Fadiman's other projects for the Encyclopaedia Britannica company, such as the Young Children's Encyclopaedia, referred to in Fadiman's notes as the "pre-reader." Fadiman was editor of Britannica's Humanities Film Series from 1969 to 1981, and this series contains two of his film reviews. Also included is a translation of Wilhelm von Humboldt's "On the External and Internal Organization of the Berlin Institutions of Higher Learning," and a letter from Fadiman harshly criticizing the piece and its author.
    - Educational Corporation Humanities Newsletter, 1967 December 14 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Film Commentaries (For the Educational Corporation) ,1969 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - "A Note on Literature" and "A Note on the Arts," circa 1970 (Box 3, Folder 3)
      (Chapter Head Notes for the 1971 Edition)
    - "On the External and Internal Organization of the Berlin Institutions of Higher Learning, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 4)
      (Translation for Great Ideas Today),
    - Young Children's Encyclopedia, circa 1970 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Series IV: Book-of-the-Month Club, undated
  This series consists of book reviews that Fadiman wrote for the Book-of-the-Month club newsletter.
  - Reviews
    - A-D, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - E-H, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - I-N, undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - O-S, undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - T-Z, undated (Box 3, Folder 10)